<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-07-11T12:47:35+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Token-mediated</title><subtitle>Work in progress 🚧</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Spoken Language Entity Linking: Embedding Model</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/07/11/spoken-language-embedding-model.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spoken Language Entity Linking: Embedding Model" /><published>2025-07-11T11:28:24+02:00</published><updated>2025-07-11T11:28:24+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/07/11/spoken-language-embedding-model</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/07/11/spoken-language-embedding-model.html"><![CDATA[<p>With out synthetic data prepared we can now train an embedding model and attempt an initial evaluation of the whole system. The embedding model will have a byt5 backbone. Why byt5? Shouldn’t the base model by a hyperparameter?  I will state without proof that this task requires a tokenizer-free approach. Standard LLMs with learned subword tokenizers are notoriously bad at understanding the internal structure of their subwords, and the phonetic similarity task requires just such understanding. There are some other tokenizer-free models, such as <a href="https://huggingface.co/google/canine-c">canine</a>, which could be interesting as well. But I’ll start with <a href="https://huggingface.co/google/byt5-small">byt5-small</a>, with mean pooling and an embedding dimension of 256. The data is a combination of transcriptions from parakeet and whisper-turbo.</p>

<p>We only have positive examples of known word-transcription pairs, so we’ll need to do negative mining to get negative examples. For want of a better option right now, let’s generate them using the <a href="https://huggingface.co/sentence-transformers/all-MiniLM-L6-v2">all-MiniLM-L6-v2</a> model.</p>

<h2 id="baseline-model-character-ngrams">Baseline model: character ngrams</h2>

<p>As mentioned in the introduction post, when going down the road of neural networks, GPUs and training models, we need to first pause and determine if all this is really necessary. Perhaps there is a simpler way.</p>

<p>We can try (bag-of) character ngrams.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>{'b': 1, 'a': 1, 'c': 1, 'h': 1, 's': 1, 't': 1, 'e': 3, 'l': 1, 'z': 1, 'n': 1, 'w': 1, 'g': 1, '^b': 1, 'ba': 1, 'ac': 1, 'ch': 1, 'hs': 1, 'st': 1, 'te': 1, 'el': 1, 'lz': 1, 'ze': 1, 'en': 1, 'nw': 1, 'we': 1, 'eg': 1, 'g$': 1, '^^b': 1, '^ba': 1, 'bac': 1, 'ach': 1, 'chs': 1, 'hst': 1, 'ste': 1, 'tel': 1, 'elz': 1, 'lze': 1, 'zen': 1, 'enw': 1, 'nwe': 1, 'weg': 1, 'eg$': 1, 'g$$': 1}
</code></pre></div></div>

<p><em>Bag of character ngrams for “Bachstelzenweg”</em></p>

<p>We need to maintain a mapping from ngrams to the index of that vector in the database. Elasticsearch can (implicitly) handle that for us. It’s only a minor annoyance, because we can use the hashing trick to simply hash the ngrams and then interpreting the hash as a uint32 we have the indices. It turns out that this is exactly what Qdrant does in their own <em>fast-embed</em> library. Hash collisions may occur but they will add little to the overall error rate.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>{1590227222: 1, 3068098019: 1, 3771431720: 1, 4117268401: 1, 2087417677: 1, 1628501593: 1, 2265248077: 3, 2295987441: 1, 2304499609: 1, 1333902333: 1, 3405261443: 1, 3716256635: 1, 267413913: 1, 62056036: 1, 2058349989: 1, 3979491815: 1, 1527449582: 1, 3808550603: 1, 1415237013: 1, 3465992959: 1, 1980614861: 1, 915182080: 1, 3224134014: 1, 3601840990: 1, 1887120473: 1, 1834228204: 1, 1813522373: 1, 123610086: 1, 3593534650: 1, 3740847369: 1, 1353835269: 1, 3920023514: 1, 2705968765: 1, 1310277804: 1, 4271617947: 1, 3836328121: 1, 486360380: 1, 4056173117: 1, 4160623159: 1, 948873334: 1, 833345316: 1, 2802396029: 1, 3026077236: 1}
</code></pre></div></div>

<p><em>Hashing the ngrams and ignoring collisions allows easy insertion to Qdrant</em></p>

<h2 id="baseline-model-evaluation">Baseline model evaluation</h2>

<p>Let’s take recall@10 as the evaluation metric - is the right answer in the top-10 results. The task is relatively hard so I don’t expect top-1 accuracy to be very good. But we can look at that too. Recall@10 also gives us an upper bound on the accuracy of a reranking approach that reranked the top 10 results.</p>

<p>Recall@10 is around 40-42%. Not great, but maybe better than expected.</p>

<p>One of issues is that the nearest neighbors are often pretty implausible (see table at the end). We cannot expect too much as a bag-of-ngrams loses all ordering information.</p>

<h2 id="embedding-model">Embedding model</h2>

<h3 id="first-attempt">First attempt</h3>

<p>Everything apparently goes fine during training, saturating at 99.6% accuracy!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/eval-set-accuracy.png" alt="training-eval-set-accuracy" /></p>

<p><em>Clearly, the model is ready to deploy without further inspection. Or is it?</em></p>

<p>So now we can embed our 500k street names and test the accuracy of the resulting vectors. Recall@10 improves, but only by 10 percentage points. Was it all worth it?</p>

<h3 id="the-solution-harder-negative-mining">The solution: hard(er) negative mining</h3>

<p>At this point, one may ask what went wrong, or abandon the whole enterprise entirely. Maybe something with training, like overfitting, or maybe the synthetic data is just too low quality. After much pondering, the most likely suspect is indeed the training data, but rather, how the negative samples were generated. We used <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">all-MiniLM-L6-v2</code> to generate negative examples, but as per the foregoing, it has no notion of phonetics, so the negative examples are unlikely to be very useful.</p>

<p>We need <em>hard negatives</em>. Maybe the baseline ngram model could generate them? This could work, but actually I decide to just use the just-trained embedding model itself to generate hard negatives. This v0 embedding model doesn’t perform great but it will generate better negatives than MiniLM.</p>

<p>After retraining, the evaluation looks much better. We get recall@10 of 78%. If we are really interested with a single result, recall@1 is 51%, and a reranker could get an upper-bound of 86% if it had access to the top-40 examples. That’s more like the kind of delta relative to the baseline I was hoping to achieve. And looking that the nearest neighbors for some example (table at end of post), the results seem a little more phonetically plausible.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>at_k</th>
      <th>recall@1</th>
      <th> </th>
      <th>recall@10</th>
      <th> </th>
      <th>recall@40</th>
      <th> </th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <th>asr</th>
      <th>parakeet</th>
      <th>whisper-turbo</th>
      <th>parakeet</th>
      <th>whisper-turbo</th>
      <th>parakeet</th>
      <th>whisper-turbo</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>sparse</td>
      <td>0.21</td>
      <td>0.22</td>
      <td>0.40</td>
      <td>0.42</td>
      <td>0.53</td>
      <td>0.53</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>dense-v0</td>
      <td>0.29</td>
      <td>0.31</td>
      <td>0.51</td>
      <td>0.52</td>
      <td>0.63</td>
      <td>0.64</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>dense-v1</td>
      <td>0.51</td>
      <td>0.52</td>
      <td>0.78</td>
      <td>0.78</td>
      <td>0.86</td>
      <td>0.86</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><em>The scores for different models and metrics on the validation set</em></p>

<h2 id="outlook">Outlook</h2>
<p>We now perform significantly better than the baseline, which leaves us at a crossroads. Where to go next to improve the system?</p>

<h3 id="reranking-two-stage-search">Reranking (two-stage search)</h3>
<p>We can just as easily train a reranker base on a biencoder. Reranking from 40 candidates could give us <em>up to</em> 35 percentage point improvement in top-1 accuracy.</p>

<h3 id="ensembling-over-sparsedense-vector-models-hybrid-search">Ensembling over sparse/dense vector models (hybrid search)</h3>
<p>The dense model does not strictly dominate the sparse model: there are cases where the correct result is in the top-10 sparse results but not in the dense, and vice-versa. So there’s possibly something to be gained from a combination. As a rough upper-bound, for e.g. the parakeet ASR model, we could check if the correct result in either the sparse top-10 <em>or</em> the dense top-10. That would give us 80%.</p>

<h3 id="end-to-end-ensembling-over-asr-models">End-to-end ensembling over ASR models</h3>
<p>The idea is this: if two ASR models make somewhat uncorrelated errors (or! if one model could be induced to provide a <em>diverse</em> nbest list), then, for a given user query, we could run both models, and generate embeddings for both transcripts. The two vectors could then be averaged. These averaged vector will have lower variance than those coming from a single model. We can quickly compute something like an upper-bound for how much better our recall@10 would be, by asking per-entity, is the right answer in the top-10 result for either asr model. This would give 86%. So there is potentially more to gain from ensembling over ASR transcriptions, rather than over vector search methods, and could improve results roughly as much as a reranker could. These results are not so precise because we are would now be considering up to 20 items rather than 10, and secondly, the results from the averaged embedding are not always coming from the union of the results of the two input vectors.</p>

<h3 id="retrieval-augmented-audio-text-hypothesis-rescoring">Retrieval-augmented audio-text hypothesis rescoring</h3>
<p>Now that we have a passable retrieval model, we could try using a multimodal llm to reanalyse the audio given 10 likely transcription candidates. The idea being, either zero shot, or via finetuning, to use the audio LLM as a reranker that not only has access to the candidate texts, but also the audio. A multimodal LLM gives us this potential and more.</p>

<h2 id="speed">Speed</h2>
<p>I can load 3k sparse vectors per second into Qdrant. Queries reach 300-200 per second. I can load 1.3k dense vectors per second, and that includes the time to embed on my local GPU. I made some use of the <a href="https://qdrant.tech/articles/indexing-optimization/">batch insert performance guide</a>, but things could be optimized further. Querying reaches 50 per second after the HNSW index hash finished construction.</p>

<h2 id="whats-next">What’s next?</h2>
<p>In the next post I’ll reveal how this system performs on the human control data.</p>

<h2 id="example-nearest-neighbors-for-each-retreival-system">Example nearest neighbors for each retreival system</h2>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>dense-v1</th>
      <th>sparse</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Salzhübelstraße</td>
      <td>Zubergasse</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Zöblitzer Schulstraße</td>
      <td>Zaubergasse</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Zollstrasse</td>
      <td>Zalm</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Zollstadlstraße</td>
      <td>Deubelsgasse</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Zabelstraße</td>
      <td>Geubelsgasse</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Zellstraße</td>
      <td>Zaungasse</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Zerzabelshofstraße</td>
      <td>Zahlgasse</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Zelzater Straße</td>
      <td>Zaltbommelstraat</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Zobelstraße</td>
      <td>Zalmstael</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Zitzelsbergerstraße</td>
      <td>Zabelstraße</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><em>Street: Salzhübelstraße, ASR transcription (parakeet): Zaltzubelstasse</em></p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>dense-v1</th>
      <th>sparse</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Im Försterkamp</td>
      <td>Im Kamp</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Im Pferdekamp</td>
      <td>Im Karkamp</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Im Forstkamp</td>
      <td>Schmitz Kamp</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Im Stadtkamp</td>
      <td>In de Kamp</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Auf dem Pützacker</td>
      <td>In de Kamp</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Auf dem Osterkamp</td>
      <td>Ihsrader Kamp</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Auf dem Strickart</td>
      <td>Im Hof Kamp</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Am Försterkamp</td>
      <td>Wilder Kamp</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Am Forstkamp</td>
      <td>Im Nesselrader Kamp</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Am Pferdekamp</td>
      <td>Im Huckinger Kamp</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><em>Street: Im Försterkamp, ASR transcription (parakeet): Imfutz der Kamp</em></p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>dense-v1</th>
      <th>sparse</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Stallgatan</td>
      <td>Stadl</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Stellagatan</td>
      <td>Stadler Garten</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Stålgatan</td>
      <td>Sologatan</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Stadler Garten</td>
      <td>Salogatan</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Stallergarten</td>
      <td>Silogatan</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Stollergarten</td>
      <td>Stadler</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Stoltsgatan</td>
      <td>Logatan</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Stilla gatan</td>
      <td>Stadlhof</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Stilla Gatan</td>
      <td>Stadlwiesen</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Sattlergang</td>
      <td>Stadlweg</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><em>Street: Stadler Garten, ASR transcription (parakeet): Stadlogaten</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[With out synthetic data prepared we can now train an embedding model and attempt an initial evaluation of the whole system. The embedding model will have a byt5 backbone. Why byt5? Shouldn’t the base model by a hyperparameter? I will state without proof that this task requires a tokenizer-free approach. Standard LLMs with learned subword tokenizers are notoriously bad at understanding the internal structure of their subwords, and the phonetic similarity task requires just such understanding. There are some other tokenizer-free models, such as canine, which could be interesting as well. But I’ll start with byt5-small, with mean pooling and an embedding dimension of 256. The data is a combination of transcriptions from parakeet and whisper-turbo.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Spoken Language Entity Linking: Synthetic Data</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/07/07/spoken-language-synthetic-data.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spoken Language Entity Linking: Synthetic Data" /><published>2025-07-07T13:01:09+02:00</published><updated>2025-07-07T13:01:09+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/07/07/spoken-language-synthetic-data</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/07/07/spoken-language-synthetic-data.html"><![CDATA[<p>Let’s take a look at the synthetic data for the spoken language entity linking system. We’ll need a list of target entities, audio of users requesting those entities, and transcriptions of that audio.</p>

<p>We can download all open street map data for our countries of interest via <a href="geofabrik.de">Geofabrik</a>. The data is a rather large protobuf file which can be converted by <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">osmconvert</code> into larger xml file. Attempts to efficiently parse this thing and extract street names via with a streaming xml parser stumped Gemini code - presumably it only has access to the same 15 year old blog posts as I could find. In the end, one can just grep for the relevant parts of the xml structure, reducing the file size considerably, then do the streaming xml parsing to precisely extract the information.</p>

<p>We end up with about 500k unique street names, which we can split into train, validation and test sets.</p>

<h1 id="text-to-speech">Text to speech</h1>

<p>The diagram in the <a href="https://nrgow.github.io/2025/07/03/spoken-language-entity-linking.html">first post</a> described the flow. <a href="https://huggingface.co/hexgrad/Kokoro-82M">Kokoro</a> can generate from phonemes, so we provide the phonemes for German street names from a German phonemizer, Dutch streets from a Dutch phonemizer, and so on - all espeak-ng phoneme models.</p>

<audio controls="">
  <source src="/assets/audio/plommonvagen_sv.wav" type="audio/mpeg" />
  Your browser does not support the audio element.
</audio>

<p><em>“Navigate to Plommonvägen”</em></p>

<audio controls="">
  <source src="/assets/audio/wustenwetzdorf_de.wav" type="audio/mpeg" />
  Your browser does not support the audio element.
</audio>

<p><em>“Navigate to Wüstenwetzdorf”</em></p>

<audio controls="">
  <source src="/assets/audio/meerswal_nl.wav" type="audio/mpeg" />
  Your browser does not support the audio element.
</audio>

<p><em>“Navigate to Meerswal”</em></p>

<p>There’s plenty of other things that could be done, like audio augmentations, considering alternative TTS providers. But there is enough to work with here for the moment. I sample 50k street names to generate audio for.</p>

<h1 id="speech-to-text">Speech to text</h1>

<p>For transcribing our synthetic data, let’s start with <em>whisper-turbo</em> - this is a more compact version of a multilingual ASR model, which in my experience can sometimes do surprisingly well with code-switched queries.</p>

<p>As an alternative, we can look at a more recent model: Parakeet (<em>nvidia/parakeet-tdt-0.6b-v2</em>) is and performant model from nvidia. It has the benefit of being ~20x faster than whisper-turbo. It currently second on the <a href="https://huggingface.co/spaces/hf-audio/open_asr_leaderboard">open ASR leaderboard</a>. It’s English-only. Despite this project being about code-switching, one of the secret premises of this project is that we might even not need to know much about other languages, at least to do this somewhat artificial entity linking task. That’s if all goes well.</p>

<p>The character error rate over the entities is pretty similar for parakeet vs. whisper-turbo (43%).</p>

<h2 id="multimodal-llms">Multimodal LLMs</h2>

<p>Some new multimodal LLMs have been released recently, most notably phi-4-multimodal and gemma-3n. These accept speech audio or text (images as well) as input. Why might such a model be interesting for a simple transcription task? Incorporation of a text-based prompt potentially allows for zero-shot or few-shot customization of the ASR component without requiring finetuning. Let’s see if that works with Gemma 3n <em>google/gemma-3n-E2B-it</em>.</p>

<h3 id="prompt-help-1">Prompt help 1</h3>

<p>All queries have the form “navigate to <street>", which I use to then extract the street name via regex. I already have to Gemma give a little help via the system prompt.</street></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“You are a helpful assistant who can transcribe audio. Users typically issue commands <em>in the imperative voice</em>.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The results are pretty bad. Character error rate is 57%. The transcriptions are not always phonetically plausible, rather making phonetically poorly-grounded semantic jumps to other entities, but we’re not here to judge ASR models. We’re trying to train a model that can correct for ASR errors, so the transcription may be valuable for that.</p>

<h3 id="prompt-help-2">Prompt help 2</h3>

<p>As an experiment, let’s give Gemma some more help with an enhanced task prompt:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Transcribe this audio file which has this structure: ‘Navigate to &lt;german/dutch/swedish street name&gt;’</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Things start to look better. Character error rate decreases to 46%: worse than parakeet or whisper but closing the gap. In less than one percent of cases, it takes the prompt a little bit too literally, and outputs “<em>navigate to &lt;german/dutch/swedish street name&gt;</em>”.</p>

<p>This example may be a little contrived, as one might rarely be able to give such a big hint, but it nicely demonstrates the flexibility and responsiveness of a multimodal model to enhanced context. In a real system, such context engineering could go in the direction of personalization and memory, or guidelines for particular terminology.</p>

<h2 id="interim-character-error-rate-evaluation">Interim character error-rate evaluation</h2>

<p>We can measure the ASR on our synthetic data, taking the character error rate of just the entity name. This evaluation is just for demonstration - maybe it is roughly correlated with end to end task performance.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th> </th>
      <th>parakeet</th>
      <th>whisper-turbo</th>
      <th>gemma_simpleprompt</th>
      <th>gemma_hintprompt</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>cer</td>
      <td>0.43</td>
      <td>0.43</td>
      <td>0.57</td>
      <td>0.46</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="transcription-examples">Transcription examples</h2>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>entity</th>
      <th>parakeet</th>
      <th>whisper-turbo</th>
      <th>gemma_simpleprompt</th>
      <th>gemma_hintprompt</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Kölvägen</td>
      <td>Schellwegan</td>
      <td>Shellvegan</td>
      <td>Shelvegen</td>
      <td>Shelvegan</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Pfarrer-Held-Straße</td>
      <td>Pfaterhilshthasa</td>
      <td>Pfaderhildstädt Hasse</td>
      <td>Powerchords to Hassa</td>
      <td>Pfahlstr</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Park de Wervelaan</td>
      <td>Parc de Vervelin</td>
      <td>Parc de Vervalan</td>
      <td>Park de Verelan</td>
      <td>Park de Verellen</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Untere Pfeifermühle</td>
      <td>Unterup Phi formula</td>
      <td>Unterupfi Formula</td>
      <td>Unter a five formula</td>
      <td>Unter der Pfeiferstraße</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Posses väg</td>
      <td>Pausus Veg</td>
      <td>Posis Veg</td>
      <td>Passus Veg</td>
      <td>Passusweg</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Am Springgarten</td>
      <td>Mspttingaten</td>
      <td>Amschptingaten</td>
      <td>Amsterdam</td>
      <td>amshiptingaten</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Broängsvägen</td>
      <td>Brunswagen</td>
      <td>Bruinswagen</td>
      <td>Braunschweig</td>
      <td>Braunschweig</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Alander Weg</td>
      <td>Aulender Vake</td>
      <td>All under VAKE</td>
      <td>all under wake</td>
      <td>Allenderwiek</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Im Alengarten</td>
      <td>him all in Gatson</td>
      <td>Im Allenghattan</td>
      <td>M All in Gaten</td>
      <td>am Allingaten</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Nordbrink</td>
      <td>NodPink</td>
      <td>Nodbdink</td>
      <td>Notepad</td>
      <td>Nordpink</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Siegelhof</td>
      <td>Ziegelhoof</td>
      <td>Ziegelhof</td>
      <td>Ziegelhof</td>
      <td>Zeughof</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Im Eisenfeld</td>
      <td>him Eisenfelt</td>
      <td>M. Eisenfeld</td>
      <td>Imfeld</td>
      <td>Immenfeld</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h1 id="human-control-audio">Human control audio</h1>

<p>It’s pretty fast to just say things, so collecting a bit of real data for validating things at the end is very doable. <em>If only there was a nice tool to handle keep track of all the wav files you need to generate</em>. Gemini code can easily cook one up in 20 minutes (that’s including a game of Minesweeper intermediate I played in between - really it was closer to 2 minutes).</p>

<p>Wielding this new tool, I can quickly generate 50 test set queries, and 50 validation set queries, which I’ll evaluate on the end to end system later.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/data-collection-tool.png" alt="Let's generate some human data too" /></p>

<p><em>Let’s generate some human data too</em></p>

<p>With some transcriptions in hand, we can now start to train the embedding model.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Let’s take a look at the synthetic data for the spoken language entity linking system. We’ll need a list of target entities, audio of users requesting those entities, and transcriptions of that audio.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Code-Switched Spoken Language Entity Linking: Intro</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/07/03/spoken-language-entity-linking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Code-Switched Spoken Language Entity Linking: Intro" /><published>2025-07-03T23:40:42+02:00</published><updated>2025-07-03T23:40:42+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/07/03/spoken-language-entity-linking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/07/03/spoken-language-entity-linking.html"><![CDATA[<p>Let’s say you’re on holiday with your voice assistant, and you want to get to <em>Bolzeschachtstraße</em>. You fire off a wake-up word, recording starts, you say: “<em>Navigate to Bolzeschachtstraße</em>”. Your voice assistant hears “<em>Baltzsakstasa</em>”. Another day, another place, this time <em>Zum Hallerbach</em>. Your voice assistant hears “<em>Tsamhalaba</em>”. No results.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/typical_scenario.png" alt="Can we fix this?" width="40%" /></p>

<p><em>Can we fix this?</em></p>

<p>What is to blame? Clearly, speech recognition has a problem. It’s great if you can fix it. On the other hand, a sufficiently smart voice assistant really <em>should</em> be able to guess, <em>even from a severely distorted transcription</em>, what is really intended, as long as the distortion is not totally wild.</p>

<p>The following blogposts will demonstrate a simple system that can take such garbled transcriptions from speech recognition and offer more accurate alternatives.</p>

<p>“<em>Code-switched</em>” means that the user will be speaking English, but will be requesting <em>non-English</em> entities. To keep things compact, I will define the universe of entities as being: German, Dutch and Swedish street names. A large enough universe to make the task challenging. I may add more as time goes on. “<em>Spoken language</em>” means that the input to the system is speech audio, to be transcribed by an ASR module.</p>

<p>The core of this system will be a text-based phonetic embedding model. The similarity function the embedding model should try to capture is this: “string <em>x</em> should be close to string <em>y</em> if <em>x</em> is a likely transcription from an ASR system of someone speaking <em>y</em>”. So, phonetics is the main invariance that should be captured, but text normalization is another, as well as the output quirks of specific ASR models. The transformer backbone of the model will by a <strong>byt5</strong> encoder. I’ll also consider a (not so?) silly baseline model based on <em>character ngrams</em>.</p>

<p>When people think of phonetic similarity, they may think of things like levenshtein distance. Unfortunately this won’t scale into a retrieval system, so we’ll have to use a sparse or dense search index. The character ngram approach might be considered an approximation of edit distance. Out of the box, it already seems pretty weak because it doesn’t respect any of the invariances we are interested in. Maybe we can overcome this. In any case, there is, to my knowledge, no plug-and-play phonetic embedding model out there, so I’ll have to build this.</p>

<p>I’ll take a look at a few different ASR models, phonetic embedding training strategies, and hybrid search &amp; reranking approaches. I’ll use <em>Qdrant</em> as the vector search engine. For ASR, I will first consider <strong>openai/whisper-large-v3-turbo</strong> and <strong>nvidia/parakeet-tdt-0.6b-v2</strong>. But maybe some more recent multimodal LLMs which can accept audio input, like <strong>google/gemma-3n-E2B-it</strong> and <strong>microsoft/phi-4-instruct</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/embedding-training-pipeline.drawio.png" alt="Here's how it will all look" /></p>

<p><em>Here’s how the embedding model will be trained</em></p>

<p>The training data for the embedding model will come from <strong>hexgrad/Kokoro-82M</strong> text-to-speech. It has the advantage that you can synthesize from phonemes. The idea is to phonemize the street name part of the TTS queries using a locale-appropriate phonemizer, to approximate an English speaker who can roughly pronounce the non-English street name. If one of the good commercial providers can do code switching better than this, I might spend O(€10) on that too.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Let’s say you’re on holiday with your voice assistant, and you want to get to Bolzeschachtstraße. You fire off a wake-up word, recording starts, you say: “Navigate to Bolzeschachtstraße”. Your voice assistant hears “Baltzsakstasa”. Another day, another place, this time Zum Hallerbach. Your voice assistant hears “Tsamhalaba”. No results.]]></summary></entry></feed>